Jimmy Hatlo Papers
Jimmy Hatlo Papers
1939-1986
Hatlo, Jimmy, 1898-1963.
15 linear ft.
Papers of the American cartoonist. Proof sheets for Little Iodine and They'll Do It Every Time, printed material, clippings, small amount of correspondence.
149042
Biographical History
James Cecil "Jimmy" Hatlo (1898-1963) was an American sports and editorial cartoonist known for his long-running strip They'll Do It Every Time.
Though born in Providence, R.I. he spent much of his youth in California, attending school in Los Angeles and beginning his newspaper career with the San Francisco Bulletin. In 1929, when a package of cartoons failed to arrive from the syndicate, sports cartoonist Hatlo was called upon to produce something, and the first They'll Do It Every Time appeared on February 5, 1929. It was syndicated in 1936 and in 1943, by popular demand, Hatlo spun off the character of Henry Tremblechin's daughter into her own strip, Little Iodine.
Hatlo went on to work for the Los Angeles Times as a sports and editorial cartoonist and spent fifteen years with the Hearst newspaper chain as an editorial cartoonist. He continued to draw They'll Do It Every Time until his death on November 30, 1963.
Hatlo's works were syndicated in the United States and abroad. He was a charter member of the National Cartoonist Society, who awarded him its Newspaper Panel Cartoon Award for 1957 and 1959.
[Portions of this biography adapted from Contemporary Authors (1998) and from Don Markstein's Toonopedia, http://www.toonopedia.com.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jimmy Hatlo Papers consists of artwork, cartoons, correspondence, memorabilia, and printed material.
Artwork consists of original artwork by Hatlo, for cartoon panels.
Cartoons consists entirely of proof sheets for Little Iodine and They'll Do It Every Time. In many cases there are two different layouts for each item, one horizontal and one vertical.
A small amount of Correspondence relates primarily to suggestions sent in by readers for gags for They'll Do It Every Time. Several are from Glen Wilkinson of San Diego. Responses to Wilkinson are from Bob Dunn, a cartoonist who worked with Hatlo on both They'll Do It Every Time and Little Iodine. There are also a few typed sheets with the lyrics to "I Wonder Who's Kissing Her Now."
Memorabilia contains clippings about Hatlo, including a reprint of an article that appeared in the Saturday Evening Post, a program and seating list from an awards ceremony in which a group called The Banshees gave Hatlo the Silver Lady award, and a Lucky Strikes cigarette ad in which Hatlo appears.
Printed material contains a variety of printed items featuring Hatlo's work, including calendars, clippings, a published collection of office-related cartoons called Office Party, some publicity for They'll, a postcard, and other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Clippings and correspondence are arranged chronologically. Cartoons are arranged chronologically for the most part, although due to size differences there is some physical discontinuity. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Related Material
has collections of more than one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see also the
George Kloek Scrapbook on Jimmy Hatlo
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Dunn, Bob, 1908-1989.; Hatlo, Jimmy, 1898-1963.; Little Iodine.; They'll do it every time.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Children -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Families -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Fathers and daughters -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Work environment -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- California.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Calendars (documents); Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Proof sheets.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eleanor Hatlo Lusignan, 1969.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - "Watching the frails...", circa June 30; Original cartoon, signed and inscribed by Hatlo; King Features Syndicate, Inc.; pen and ink; 11" x 14" (Oversize 1)
  - They'll Do It Every Time, 24 May 1948; Original artwork for panel cartoon; 10" x 12.5" (Oversize 1)
- Cartoons
  - Little Iodine, proof sheets
    - Sunday strips, 1944; 1946-1952 (Oversize 1)
    - Sunday strips, 1953-1957 (Oversize 2)
    - Sunday strips, 1958-1961 (Oversize 3)
  - They'll Do It Every Time, proof sheets
    - Daily strips, 1939-1942; 1944-1945 (Oversize 5)
    - Daily strips, 1946-1951 (Oversize 4)
      See also Artwork: They'll Do It Every Time.
    - Daily strips, 1952 (Oversize 5)
    - Daily strips, 1953-1955 (Oversize 6)
    - Daily strips, 1956-1957 (Oversize 5)
    - Daily strips, 1958-1964 (Oversize 7)
    - Sunday strips, 1948-1954 (Oversize 8)
    - Sunday strips, 1955-1958 (Oversize 9)
    - Sunday strips, 1959-1963 (Oversize 10)
  - Miscellaneous, proof sheets
    - Undated and/or unidentified proof sheets (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1957; 1979,; 1982-1983,; 1986,; undated (Box 1)
    Most of the correspondence relates to suggestions sent in by readers for They'll Do It Every Time, including a number from Glen Wilkinson of San Diego; the responses to Wilkinson are from cartoonist Bob Dunn, who worked with Hatlo on both They'll Do It and Little Iodine
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings about Hatlo, 1949-1951; 1955,; 1959-1960,; 1963,; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950; undated; "Silver Lady" cartoonist of the year award program with seating list, Lucky Strikes ad featuring Hatlo (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Calendars, They'll Do It Every Time, 1940; 1948-1949,; 1953,; 1956-1958; 2 copies of each (Box 1)
  - Clippings of Hatlo's work, 1957-1986; includes three notebooks with clippings pasted in, and some clippings of other cartoonists' work; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Office Party, 1959; collection of cartoons, published by Grosset and Dunlap; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Publicity for They'll Do It Every Time, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, postcard, party program, calendar, etc. (Box 1)